Catherine Alexander papers, Inclusive: 1871-1962, undated, Bulk: 1930-1959, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Catherine Alexander papers
Inclusive: 1871-1962, undated, Bulk: 1930-1959, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
1675
Alexander, Catherine Sarah Bennett
4 document boxes
The Catherine Alexander papers consist of correspondence, literary productions, books, and artifacts collected and produced by Mrs. Catherine Alexander.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Catherine Bennett was born on 1879 January 12 to Minter and Henrietta Bennett. She married Lewis W. Alexander on 1903 June 12 in Daviess, Kentucky. The Alexanders soon moved to San Antonio, Texas, where Lewis Alexander owned the Coca Cola Bottling Co.. The two were active members of their church and participated in many short-term missions trips abroad. Through those trips, Catherine developed relationships with missionaries from all over the globe. The majority of these papers are photographs and books related to Catherine’s missionary network.
Unfortunately, the family’s next 30 years would be marked by a series of tragedies. The Alexanders lost their second son, Lewis W. Alexander Jr., at only six months of age in 1920. During a missions trip to Kenya on 1935 February 19, Lewis W. Alexander Sr. died and was buried in Nairobi. Only four years later, in 1939, Catherine’s other son, James Quint Alexander, died at the age of 35.
After her husband passed away, Catherine moved to Waco, Texas, where she donated a great deal of her fortune to Baylor University. She was the largest benefactor to building Catherine Alexander Hall, a new Baylor dormitory for women. The dormitory was dedicated on 1941 January 31, and included an apartment for Catherine, who would live in the hall until her death on 1968 February 4. Catherine’s presence in the hall, her open door policy for the students, and her leadership of many on-campus missions groups led to her being christened “Mother" Alexander by many of her students.
Scope and Content
The Catherine Alexander papers consists of correspondence, literary productions, books, and photographic materials collected and produced by Mrs. Catherine Alexander. The majority of the materials relate to Catherine’s work as a missionary with the Southern Baptist Convention.
The Catherine Alexander papers provide important insight into the network of conservative Protestant missionaries sent out from the United States during the first half of the 20th Century. The materials were collected by Mrs. Catherine Alexander, a widowed Southern Baptist missionary who became a benefactor to Baylor University and the beloved “Mother” Alexander to its students.
Although Catherine Alexander is probably best known for her financial and personal legacy to Baylor, it is her legacy among missionary families that is preserved most clearly in these papers. Therefore, the Catherine Alexander Papers would be an excellent resource for anyone interested in early 20th century Protestantism, missions, or the role of women in the Southern Baptist denomination.
Arrangement
Prior to this finding aid the Catherine Alexander papers were partially organized by material type and topic, but not all of the materials were included.
Currently, the collection is organized into four series: I: Correspondence, II: Literary Productions, III: Books, IV: Photographic Materials
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 1675. Acquired 1977-07-28
Related Resources
Related references
“Alexander Hall To Be Dedicated by Mrs. E. D. Head.” The Daily Lariat. 1941 January 31. Accessed 2013 August 20.
Find A Grave, Inc. “Catherine Alexander.” Memorial #18712880. Databases. Accessed 2013 August 23.
Catherine Alexander Hall [Vertical File], The Texas Collection, Baylor University.
“Freshman Girls Live in New Dormitory.” The Daily Lariat. 1941 May 10.
"Texas, Deaths (New Index, New Images), 1890-1976." FamilySearch. Accessed 2013 August 23.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor University -- History -- 20th century.; Southern Baptist Convention -- History -- 20th century.
Subjects
Baptist universities and colleges -- Texas -- Waco -- History.; Baptist Women.; Baptists -- Brazil.; Baptists -- Missions.; Baptists -- Texas -- Waco -- History.; Missionaries.
Genres
Correspondence.; Directories.; Photographs.
- Correspondence, 1939-1961, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  This series consists of a letter to Catherine Alexander from Baylor President and Governor Pat Neff, and numerous photo greeting cards sent by missionaries around the world.
  - Letter to Catherine Alexander from Pat Neff, 1939 May 30 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Greeting Cards: Photographic: South America, 1939-1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Greeting Cards: Photographic: Japan, China, and Indonesia, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Greeting Cards: Photographic: General, 1953-1961, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Literary Productions, 1931-1958, undated; 2
  This series contains numerous printed materials related to Catherine’s involvement with missions work and the Southern Baptist Convention. It also includes a guest book signed by visitors to her apartment in Catherine Alexander Hall at Baylor.
  - Printed Materials: San Marcus Baptist Academy Trustees List, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Printed Materials, 1931-1958, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Certificates: National Geographic Society, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Guest Book, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Directory: Womans' Bible Class, First Baptist Church, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Directory: Missionary Personnel of the Southern Baptist Convention, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Directory: Year Book of the Woman's Missionary Union, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bookmarks, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Programs: Missionary Festival First Baptist Church, 1945 April 27-30 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Paintings, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Poetry Booklets: L. Young Correthers, 1934-1940 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Story Booklet: "The Story of Effie Roe Maddox": Sarah Frances Gill Maddox, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Religious Publications: Christmas, 1955-1956, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Religious Publications: "Seek and Ye Shall Find:" A.C. SoRelle, 1955 March (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Religious Publications: General, 1928-1956, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Signature Album, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Guest Book: Catherine Alexander's Apartment, Alexander Hall, 1940-1958 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Books, 1871-1944; 3
  General condition: Average.
  This series contains a travelers guide to Africa and multiple Bibles in various languages. This series is in average to good condition.
  - The African Handbook and Traveler's Guide, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Foreign Language Bibles: Russian and Portuguese, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Foreign Language Bibles: Yoruba, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Bible: American Bible Society Pocket Bible, 1871 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Photographic Materials, 1935-1962, undated; 4
  This series contains photographs collected by Catherine Alexander, primarily relating to her missions work. Many of the photos are of other foreign missionaries and their families.
  Index Terms
  Genres
  Photographic print
  - Missions: Africa, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Missions: Indonesia, Japan, China, 1948, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Missions: South America: Argentina and Chile, 1942-1950, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Missions: South America: Uruguay and Paraguay, 1938-1957, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Missions: South America: Brazil, 1939-1942, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Missions: South America: General, 1939-1954, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Missions: South America: General, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Seminary: Zurich, 1948, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - General, 1935-1962 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - General (1 of 4), undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - General (2 of 4), undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - General (3 of 4), undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - General (4 of 4), undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - State Margaret Fund Photograph, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)